Cholmondeley-Pennell, H. (Henry), 1837-1915. Papers on fishing (MS Eng 1591): Guide.
Papers on fishing,
1877-1907.
Houghton Library, Harvard College Library, Harvard University
This collection is shelved offsite at the Harvard Depository. See access restrictions below for additional information.
MS Eng 1591
Cholmondeley-Pennell, H. (Henry), 1837-1915.
1 box (1 linear ft.)
Correspondence with publishers, fishing tackle manufacturers, and others, concerning writings on fishing by British naturalist and editor, Henry Cholmondeley-Pennell. Also includes drafts of autograph manuscripts, and clippings and autograph notes on fishing, and samples of fishing line and flies.
Purchased with the Minot Fund; received: 1918 Nov. 14. Recataloged from F 5.14.25*
This collection is not housed at the Houghton Library but is shelved offsite at the Harvard Depository. Retrieval requires advance notice. Readers should check with Houghton Public Services staff to determine what material is offsite and retrieval policies and times.
Cholmondeley-Pennell (1837-1915) was a British naturalist and editor who published poetry and many volumes on coarse-fly and deep-sea fishing. Two of his most well-know books were: Badminton library of sports and pastimes: Fishing. With contributions from other authors and The modern practical angler: a complete guide to fly-fishing, bottom-fishing trolling.
Organized into two series:
I. Correspondence with H. (Henry) Cholmondeley-Pennell
II. Other materials
Early letters concern his various writings on fishing. Correspondence circa 1902-1905 concerns the revision for a new edition of a volume in the Badminton Library of Fishing. With contributions from other authors: Pike and other coarse fish. Includes letters to and from printers, publishers, writers of articles within this volume, fishing experts, fishing equipment suppliers, and fishing enthusiasts. Also includes samples of fishing line and fishing flies.
The library has several works by this author containing his autograph notes in preparation for later editions, with autograph letters by him, inserted. See: F 214.5.25*, F 214.5.30*, F 214.5.31*, F 214.5.36*, F 214.5.37*, F 1635.14.72*, and F 1650.13.36*.
- I. Correspondence with H. (Henry) Cholmondeley-Pennell
  - Bean, Arthur. Letter to HCP, 1885., (1); 1 folder.
  - Bemrose Sons. Letter to HCP, 1903., (2); 1 folder.
  - Blunt, Wilfrid Scawen, 1840-1922. Letter to HCP, undated., (3); 1 folder.
  - C. Farwell Co. Correspondence with HCP, 1902-1905., (4); 1 folder.
    Fishing tackle manufacturer.
  - Clay, G. Hollis. Letter to HCP, 1885., (5); 1 folder.
  - Davies, G. Christopher (George Christopher), 1849-1922. Correspondence with HCP, 1903., (6); 1 folder.
    Concerns Davies' article on "Fishing in the Norfolk Broads." Includes revised proofs of this article.
  - F. J. Ogden-Smith. Letters to HCP, 1886-1903., (7); 1 folder.
  - Foster Bros. (Ashbourne, England). Correspondence with HCP, 1888-1904 and undated., (8); 1 folder.
    Includes samples of fishing line.
  - Francis, Francis. Letters to HCP, undated., (9); 1 folder.
  - Halford, Frederic M. (Frederic Michael), 1844-1914. Correspondence with HCP, 1903., (10); 1 folder.
  - Hall, H.S. Correspondence with HCP, 1884-1903 and undated., (11); 1 folder.
  - Hardy Brothers Ltd. Correspondence with HCP, 1903-1905., (12); 1 folder.
  - Holt, Cardley C. Letter to HCP, undated., (13); 1 folder.
  - Jardine, Alfred, recipient. Letter from HCP, 1903., (14); 1 folder.
  - Kelso, E. H. G. Letters to HCP, 1877 and undated., (15); 1 folder.
  - Kelson, Geo. M. (George M.). Letter to HCP, 1892., (16); 1 folder.
  - Locking, W. R. Letter to HCP, 1886., (17); 1 folder.
  - Long, Henry A. Correspondence with HCP, 1903., (18); 1 folder.
  - Longmans, Green, and Co. Correspondence with HCP, 1903., (19); 1 folder.
    Publisher.
  - Longmans, Green, and Co. Correspondence with HCP, 1904-1907., (20); 1 folder.
  - Marston, Robert Bright, 1853-1927. Correspondence with HCP, 1903-1905., (21); 1 folder.
    Marston at the Fishing Gazette. Includes fishing flies.
  - McNeill, Malcolm. Letter to HCP, 1884., (22); 1 folder.
  - North of England Rod Works, recipient. Letter from HCP, 1904., (23); 1 folder.
  - P. D. Malloch. Correspondence with HCP, 1903., (24); 1 folder.
  - Peacock, Colonel. Correspondence with HCP, 1903., (25); 1 folder.
  - Ramsbottom, Robert. Letter to HCP, undated., (26); 1 folder.
  - Rosslyn, James Francis Harry St. Clair-Erskine, Earl of, 1869-1939. Letter to HCP, 1896., (27); 1 folder.
  - S. Allcock Co. Letter to HCP, 1896., (28); 1 folder.
    Includes a card of samples of fishing line.
  - Sandeman, R. Letters to HCP, undated., (29); 1 folder.
  - Scanlan, Mrs., recipient. Letter from HCP, 1907., (30); 1 folder.
  - Senior, William, 1839?-1920. Correspondence with HCP, 1903., (31); 1 folder.
  - Spottiswoode Co. Correspondence with HCP, 1903-1904., (32); 1 folder.
    Printers.
  - Stamford, Charles. Correspondence with HCP, 1903., (33); 1 folder.
  - Stoddard, Thomas. Letter to HCP, undated., (34); 1 folder.
  - Trubritt, R. D. Letter to HCP, undated., (35); 1 folder.
  - Wm. Bartleet Sons. Correspondence with HCP, 1902-1905., (36); 1 folder.
  - Yardley, W. Letters to HCP, 1883., (37); 1 folder.
  - [Unidentified correspondent], Letter to HCP, undated., (38); 1 folder.
- II. Other materials
  - Cholmondeley-Pennell, H. (Henry), 1837-1915. Notes on fishing: autograph manuscripts, undated., (39); 1 folder.
    Many are fragments only.
  - Cholmondeley-Pennell, H. (Henry), 1837-1915. Revisions to writings on fishing: typescripts, typescript carbons, autograph manuscripts, undated., (40); 2 folders.
    Partial manuscripts with autograph manuscript revisions and annotations. Includes titles: The 2-hook worm tackle for salmon and its inception, Addendum A., For chapter on live bating, and Page 138.
  - Clippings on fishing, ca. 1883-1905., (41); 1 folder.